Finding Aid for Unistrut Corporation (Wayne, Mich.) Records 1922-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Unistrut Corporation (Wayne, Mich.) records 1922-1990, 1929-1966
Unistrut Corporation (Wayne, Mich.)
(in 3 boxes)
2.5 linear feet
Company established by Charles Attwood who was inventor and developer of a system of precast metal frame construction that came to be known as the Unistrut system. The company was originally known as Deceleco. The record group includes background and historical information about Unistrut; job files containing records pertaining to the planning and execution of Deceleco's contracts, 1929-1932; product literature and catalogs, 1927-1981; publications resulting from research into the Unistrut system of construction; and photographs.
0076 Bb 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred by Kevin R. Godin in 2000 (donor number 8941 ).
The record group is open for research.
Deceleco, Inc., the predecessor company to the Unistrut Corporation, was established in 1924 by Charles Attwood, a graduate of the University of Michigan School of Architecture. Attwood, upon graduation, had first worked as a machinist with Willys Overland Company in Ohio. He then formed his own architectural firm of Attwood and Trysell. This firm soon dissolved and Attwood next joined the architectural firm of Smith, Hinchman & Grylls Associates. There he was given the assignment of designing powerhouses to contain electrical circuits, generators, and switches. Little information then existed about methods to safely house electricity powerhouses. After studying the problem, Attwood determined that use of cell structures would reduce the rate of fires resulting from sparks let off when switches were thrown. At the time, there were few manufacturers who could manufacture the parts that Attwood needed for the cell structures. In order to produce them himself, he established Deceleco, Inc. in 1924. In 1926, he moved the company to Wayne, Michigan.
A few years after Deceleco, Inc. was established, a metal-clad switch gear was introduced into the market. Attwood recognized the impact that this innovation would have on his company. In order to keep Deceleco, Inc. competitive, he addressed problems related to electrical powerhouses: the lack of housing for electrical wires and conduits, and the lack of plumb and square floors for the powerhouses. Attwood devised an adjustable frame system which could support heavy loads solved both of these problems.
At the end of the 1930s, Attwood invented and developed a system of precast metal frame construction that would become the cornerstone of the Unistrut Corporation. This method of construction does not require that holes be bored into steel members in order that they be fastened together. Instead a nut that slides in a channel locks the structural elements tightly together. The Attwood System of Frame Construction, also known as the Unistrut system, was advertised in Attwood's first product catalog appearing in 1940. Over the next seven years, Attwood's factory in Wayne, Michigan, was outfitted so that it could independently produce all of the components needed for the Unistrut system (previously produced by a company in New York state and sold through distributors). George W. Butler, one of these distributors, was very successful in selling the Unistrut system. Butler secured the international marketing rights and incorporated the Unistrut Products Corporation in 1944. Butler developed Unistrut distribution centers in many parts of the United States.
The 1950s witnessed further expansion and international marketing by the company. In 1957, Unistrut exhibited a building constructed entirely from the company's metal framing system at the International Trade Fairs. In 1962, Unistrut Corporation acquired the Unistrut Products Corporation so that all business activities associated with Unistrut products was conducted from the Wayne, Michigan, location. The Telespar and Space Frame systems were also developed during this time period. In 1964, Charles Attwood died.
The 1970s saw a shift in the focus of the Unistrut Corporation. Rhett W. Butler joined the company and instigated a move from a manufacturing-centered business to an international marketing enterprise. (Butler became president of Unistrut in 1971.) The company also prepared to offer stock for sale. Preparations to "go public" included clearing the title to all patents, copyrights, and trademarks, as well as purchasing several associated subsidiaries. The company also merged with GTE Sylvania, Inc. in 1973. Manufacturing facilities for Unistrut products were established in England, Mexico, Australia, New Zealand, the Netherlands, and Canada. The Color Line partition system was added to the company's product line in 1977.
In the beginning of the 1980s, the company focused on utilizing computers to control inventory. Employee teams were also formed to improve the quality of the company's products. In 1984, the Unistrut management was informed of GTE's decision to divest Unistrut. The Unistrut Management bid for the ownership of Unistrut during the remainder of 1984 and the beginning of 1985. In January, 1986, Unistrut Management signed a purchasing contract with GTE.
Unistrut continued to develop in the 1990s. One of the projects tackled by the company during this time was the construction of the Shah Alam Stadium in Malaysia. The stadium was built using Unistrut's space frame system. It seats 81,000 people and incorporates the longest free standing arch in the world.
The Unistrut Corporation records cover the establishment and development of two companies founded by the architect Charles Attwood. The records offer information about the products produced and sold by these companies. Included in the records are background information pertaining to the Deceleco and Unistrut companies, job files documenting the planning and execution of Deceleco contracts, catalogs and product literature, publications that resulted from research into the Unistrut system of construction, and photographs largely depicting tests of the space frame system designed by Charles Attwood.
Subjects:
Architecture.; Attwood, Charles.; Building, Iron and steel.; Construction industry--Michigan--Wayne.; Deceleco Corporation.; Framing (Building); Unistrut Corporation (Wayne, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Architecture.; Building construction.; Building systems.; Construction industry.; Deceleco Corporation.; Unistrut Corporation (Wayne, Mich.)
Contributors:
Attwood, Charles.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Background Materials 1922-1966
  The Background Materials series (.25 linear feet) includes information pertaining to the history of the Deceleco and Unistrut companies. It incorporates a company history, correspondence and information about some of the materials and suppliers that Deceleco used. The folder entitled "Company History" contains a brief but valuable overview of how the company developed since its establishment in 1924. This series spans the dates 1922-1966.
  - Company History (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1925-1931, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1926-1931 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - Deceleco Weekly Bulletin 1929 (Box 1)
    - Unistrut Top Ten Superheroes 1980 (Box 1)
  - Patents 1927-1931 (Box 1)
  - Product Research and Suppliers 1922-1962, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Job Files 1929-1932
  The Job Files series (.75 linear feet) includes records pertaining to the planning and execution of Deceleco's contracts. The records span the years 1929-1932. They are organized by the name of the job and include plans, cost estimates for materials, correspondence with the customers and contractors, and other miscellaneous information. These files are valuable illustrations of the type of work performed by Deceleco and the processes involved in accomplishing it.
  - Ambler Asbestos Shingle and Sheathing Company 1930 (Box 1)
  - American Gas and Electric Company 1930 (Box 1)
  - Bangor Hydro-Electric Company 1931 (Box 1)
  - Board of Water and Electric Light Commission 1929 (Box 1)
  - Buick Motor Company 1931 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Steel Company 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Central Main Power Company 1930 (Box 1)
  - City of Hamilton, OH 1929-1931, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Commonwealth Edison Company 1930-1931, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Detroit Water Board 1927-1932, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Detroit Windsor Tunnel 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - General Electric Company 1926-1931, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Hatzel and Buehler 1931 (Box 1)
  - Holzer Sheet Metal Works 1931 (Box 1)
  - Inland Steel Company 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Jersey Central Power and Light 1929-1931, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Monogehola West Penn Public Service Company 1930 (Box 1)
  - National Tube Company 1930 (Box 1)
  - New Jersey Power Company 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Northern States Power Company 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - Oklahoma Gas and Electric Company 1929-1930, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Electric Company 1929-1930, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Railroad Building 1930 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Railroad Company 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Pubic Lighting Commission, City of Detroit 1929-1931, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Public Service Company of Colorado (Box 1)
  - Vacuum Oil Company 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Vanadium Corporation of America 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - Westinghouse Electric and Manufacturing Company 1929-1930, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Product Literature and Catalogs 1927-1981
  Spanning the years 1927-1981, the Product Literature and Catalogs series (.5 linear feet) offers information about the companies' products. Catalogs illustrate the variety of products produced by Deceleco and Unistrut. Both the catalogs and the product literature offer information about the construction systems devised by Charles Attwood. The broad span of years covered by this series illustrates how the products developed over time.
  - Deceleco
    - Cell Structure Construction 1941 (Box 1)
    - Cell Structures Catalog 1 1927 (Box 1)
    - Cell Structures Catalog 2 (Box 1)
    - The Unistrut 1940 (Box 1)
  - Unistrut
    - Catalog 3 1942 (Box 2)
    - Catalog 3 P-1000 Series 1956 (Box 2)
    - Catalog 3A P-1000 Series Supplement 1949 (Box 2)
    - Catalog 4 P-2000/4000/6000/7000 Series 1949-1957 (Box 2)
    - Catalog 5 1958-1975 (Box 2)
    - Catalog 6 1966 (Box 2)
    - Catalog 700 1956 (Box 2)
    - Catalog 8 1977 (Box 2)
    - Catalog 9A 1980 (Box 2)
    - Catalog 10A 1981 (Box 2)
    - Color Line System 1958-1978, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Fluorescent Fixture Suspension 1955 (Box 2)
    - General Bulletin 1943 (Box 2)
    - Kurlok Tray Systems 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Met-L Flooring Systems 1962 (Box 2)
    - Metal Framing 1958-1964 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1961-1975 (Box 2)
    - Partitions 1955 (Box 2)
    - Perfo Strut 1960 (Box 2)
    - Price Schedules 1950-1966 (Box 2)
    - Space Frame System 1959-1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - System of Construction 1957 (Box 2)
- Research and Publications 1956-1990
  The Research and Publications series (.5 linear feet) is comprised of publications primarily resulting from research into the Unistrut system of construction. It spans the years from 1956-1990. Unistrut cooperated with the College of Architecture and Design at the University of Michigan to test various aspects of the company's space frame system and construction system. These publications include technical data and specifications. This series also includes a few reports on the Shah Alam Stadium. Unistrut undertook the building of this stadium which seats 81,000 people in Malaysia in the 1990s. In 1995, the structure incorporated the longest free-standing arch in the world.
  - Miscellaneous 1968 (Box 2)
  - Report on Unistrut Space Frame System 1955-1975, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Research News, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Shah Alam Sports Complex 1990 (Box 2)
  - Shah Alam Stadium 1995 (Box 2)
  - Structural Analysis of Unistrut Space Frame Roofs, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Unistrut School Construction, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Unistrut System of Construction, 1956 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (.5 linear feet) contains photographs of the Deceleco and Unistrut corporations. The majority of these photographs depict a series of tests of the space frame system. Other images in the series depict Charles Attwood, Unistrut company meetings, structures built by the Unistrut, and the Deceleco company building.
  - Charles Attwood (Box 3)
  - Celebrations and Meetings (Box 3)
  - Components (Box 3)
  - Deceleco (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Shah Alam Sports Complex (Box 3)
  - Space Frame Tests (Box 3)
  - Structures (Box 3)